Okay, we're on.
So Rabbi Winzer did us all a favor and got us really
close to the end of the discussion we've been having about the
אנדרוגינוס. Androgynus.
Now I've wrecked his,
not sure what happened here.
Well,
whatever
it will be. All right. Rabbi Winzer has gotten us pretty far
in the discussion of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש Resh
Lakish with regards to the אנדרוגינוס, Androgynus, the hermaphrodite, which we've been
dealing with up to this point. If you recall, the question is
we talk about a hermaphrodite getting married and the fact
that according to רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose and רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon,
a hermaphrodite can cause his wife to eat תרומה. Teruma. So רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says even מתנות כהונה, Matnot Kehuna, even the parts
of the
even things that are really קודש ממש, Kodesh mamash, like parts of
the sacrifices. And ריש לקיש Resh Lakish says no, no, not those
things. And the position that the גמרא Gemara takes is that רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is saying
תרומה בזמן
הזה Teruma bizman hazeh is דאורייתא. De-Oraita. Because the משנה Mishna tells
us that the hermaphrodite can feed his wife תרומה, Teruma, that tells
us that he can feed her any kind of קודש, Kodesh, which
is not necessarily the case if תרומה בזמן הזה Teruma bizman hazeh
were דרבנן. De-Rabbanan. So now the גמרא Gemara asks: וסבר רבי יוחנן
תרומה בזמן הזה דאורייתא? Ve-sabar Rabbi Yochanan Teruma bizman hazeh De-Oraita? Is
it really the case that תרומה Teruma today is דאורייתא? De-Oraita? So
we're on פב עמוד ב, Pey Bet Amud Bet, close to the
end of the עמוד, Amud, one, two, three, four, five, six, seven,
eight, nine, ten, eleven lines from the bottom approximately.
פב עמוד א, Pey Bet Amud Aleph, excuse me. וסבר רבי יוחנן
תרומה בזמן הזה דאורייתא? Ve-sabar Rabbi Yochanan Teruma bizman hazeh De-Oraita? והתניא
שתי קופות אחת של חולין ואחת של תרומה ולפניהם שתי סאין אחת
של חולין ואחת של תרומה ונפלו אלו בתוך אלו הרי אלו מותרין
שאני אומר תרומה לתוך תרומה נפלה וחולין לתוך חולין נפלה. Ve-ha-tanya shtei
kuppot achat shel chullin ve-achat shel Teruma ve-lifneichem shtei se'in achat shel
chullin ve-achat shel Teruma ve-naflu elu be-toch elu harei elu mutarin she-ani
omer Teruma le-toch Teruma nafla ve-chullin le-toch chullin nafla. So we have
the following
case: two baskets, one of חולין chullin and one of תרומה, Teruma,
and next to them or above them are sitting two סאין, se'in,
a certain measurement, also of חולין chullin and תרומה, Teruma, and the
סאין se'in fall over. They get,
they fall into the baskets of תרומה Teruma and חולין. chullin. And
our question is what do we do? We have a ספק safek
and we're not sure how to handle it. So the ברייתא Baraita
tells us that what we're dealing with here is all okay because
we say, okay, the תרומה Teruma fell into the תרומה Teruma basket
and the חולין chullin fell into the חולין chullin basket and it's
no problem.
ואמר ריש לקיש, Ve-amar Resh Lakish, and on this case ריש לקיש
Resh Lakish said, והוא שרבו חולין על התרומה. Ve-hu she-rabbu chullin al
ha-Teruma. And this is specific to a case where the חולין chullin
that's sitting in the basket is greater than the סאה se'ah of
תרומה Teruma that is sitting above it or next to it. In
other words, even if
the תרומה Teruma had fallen into the חולין chullin basket, we'd still
be okay because there would be more חולין chullin than תרומה. Teruma.
And in
איסור דרבנן, Issur De-Rabbanan, we say that they're בטל ברוב. batel be-rov.
We don't require שישים. shishim. We don't require sixty parts. It's enough
just to have רוב. rov. So that's pretty clear evidence that ריש
לקיש Resh Lakish holds תרומה Teruma is דרבנן. De-Rabbanan. And what about
רבי יוחנן? Rabbi Yochanan? ורבי יוחנן אמר אף על פי שלא רבו
חולין על התרומה. Ve-Rabbi Yochanan amar af al pi she-lo rabbu chullin
al ha-Teruma. Even though there's not more חולין chullin than תרומה. Teruma.
In other words, even though we can't guarantee
that if the תרומה Teruma had fallen into the חולין, chullin,
it would have been okay, we still say that it's all okay
because תרומה Teruma fell into the תרומה Teruma and חולין chullin fell
into the חולין. chullin. So he's actually more lenient than him? Yep,
in both cases, he's also he's more
lenient. Interestingly,
right, exactly. בשלמא לריש לקיש קסבר בדרבנן. Bishlama le-Resh Lakish kasavar be-De-Rabbanan.
נמי ריבוייא הוא דבעינן. nami ribuya hu debainan. So okay, I understand
ריש לקיש, Resh Lakish, because ריש לקיש Resh Lakish says okay in
cases where you have some kind of איסור דרבנן, issur derabanan, it's
enough to have רוב. rov. It's not to have more חולין chullin
than תרומה. terumah. אלא לרבי יוחנן קשיא. Ella l’Rabbi Yochanan kashya. Excuse
me, for רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan we have a קשיא. kashya.
So right, why does רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan seem to think that
even though we're... think that it's still, that it's still okay even
if there's more חולין chullin on the תרומה, terumah, especially if you
want to say that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan thinks that תרומה terumah
is דאורייתא? de'oraita? If it's דאורייתא, de'oraita, it's certainly not going to
be בטל ברוב. batel berov. So we're stuck. So we say הא
מני? ha mani? Who are we talking about in this case of
תרומה? terumah?
רבנן היא. Rabbanan hi. This is a position of the people who
disagree with רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose in that... that in our משנה
mishnah we have the case of... it's רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose who
says that a
אנדרוגינוס... androgynos... a hermaphrodite is able to feed her... his wife
תרומה. terumah.
So he says okay, this is people who disagree with רבי יוסי,
Rabbi Yose, this particular
position. ואנא דאמרי כרבי יוסי. ve'ana d'amri k'Rabbi Yose. Right?
So this ברייתא braita you're bringing me is not relevant because the
ברייתא braita you're bringing me is according to the position that disagrees
with the position that I hold in our
משנה. mishnah. דתניא בסדר עולם אשר ירשו אבותיך
וירשתה. detanya beSeder Olam asher yarshu avotecha vireshtah. He's going to prove
that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose does hold that תרומה terumah is דאורייתא.
de'oraita. סדר עולם Seder Olam has a lot of halachic consequences? Apparently.
Apparently. By the way, I'm not sure that this סדר עולם Seder
Olam is the same סדר עולם Seder Olam that we refer to
in other places. The history. The history. Although it does
mean... Chaim Milikowsky has written a lot about סדר עולם. Seder Olam.
Yes.
So, I mean, has claiming... claims that סדר עולם Seder Olam is
extremely early. So it's possible that we're talking about the same סדר
עולם. Seder Olam. According to what else would it be? It could
be a later work. There were a number of versions of... sorry?
A number of versions of סדר עולם? Seder Olam? No, it's just
a matter of dating it. But there were different texts at different...
back
like one says that רבקה Rivka was three when she got married
and another says she was fourteen. Well there are versions of סדר
עולם. Seder Olam. The question is what exactly... I mean the real
question is the סדר עולם Seder Olam that gets into the history
of sort of more recent events with regards to the תלמוד Talmud
and things like that. So I don't know. Can you give a
short description of what is סדר עולם Seder Olam for...
I mean I'm not a big expert on סדר עולם. Seder Olam.
סדר עולם... Seder Olam...
it's trying to fill in the gaps that are not included in
the narrative in חומש. Chumash. But it gets very... gets all through
בית שני. Bayis Sheni. It discusses the history
of the different exiles and
the... like a timeline. Yeah, it's a book of history. It's early,
like a bunch of people imagine? Yes, it seems to be a
conglomerate work. It looks very much like sort of our rabbinic literature,
like the תלמוד Talmud or something like that, like a collection of
ברייתות braitot or something like that. This is attributed to רבי יוסי?
Rabbi Yose? Maybe attributed, I don't know. It would make sense in
this case. So it says here coming up? Yes, although it may
be who's saying this particular ברייתא braita in סדר עולם. Seder Olam.
In any case,
yeah, that's as much as I feel comfortable saying about סדר עולם.
Seder Olam. I really don't have a lot of... It's not like
the חומש Chumash and you know this happened and that happened and
the other thing happened. It is a discussion of history in terms
of what happens going back to the תורה Torah and coming all
the way to... סדר עולם. Seder Olam. So it's like reading the
תורה Torah but it's just סדר עולם. Seder Olam. Except that it
doesn't sound like פסוקים, pesukim, it sounds like
ברייתא. braita. Okay. Because אמר amar so-and-so this is what happened then.
I think there's less אמר, amar, but you'll see. I mean... so
it says: דתניא בסדר עולם אשר ירשו אבותיך וירשתה. Detanya beSeder Olam
asher yarshu avotecha vireshtah. It brings a
פסוק. pasuk. ירושה ראשונה ושנייה יש להם ושלישית אין להם. Yerushah rishonah
u'shniyah yesh lahem u'shlishit ein lahem. That's the ברייתא. braita.
So we have this פסוק, pasuk, that your fathers will come to
the inheritance that your fathers inherited and you will inherit it. So
a single ירושה yerushah and even a second ירושה. yerushah. they have,
but they don't have the third. So רש"י Rashi explains what are
we talking about? We're talking about the first ירושה yerusha as the
ירושה yerusha of יהושע בן נון Yehoshua Bin Nun when he took
over the land and the second ירושה yerusha is when עזרא Ezra
came back and brought all the Jews back to ארץ ישראל. Eretz
Yisrael. But he says there's no need for a third ירושה yerusha
because ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael is still קודש. kodesh. ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael is still קודש kodesh after the second time. After the first
time the קדושה kedusha of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael was eliminated. There's
סוגיות, sugyot, actually several סוגיות sugyot about what's the story with the
קדושת ארץ ישראל. kedushat Eretz Yisrael. How does it, does it come,
does it go, does it stay? In any case, the position that
רש"י Rashi presents here and I think it's the position of the
גמרא Gemara is
after the ירושה yerusha of יהושע בן נון, Yehoshua Bin Nun, so
then there was גלות בבל. Galut Bavel. גלות בבל Galut Bavel eliminated
the קדושה kedusha of ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. When עזרא Ezra brought
the Jews back, that was a second קדושה. kedusha. They made it
קודש kodesh again. But there's no need to do it again, as
רש"י Rashi says, גלות טיטוס Galut Titus doesn't do anything. The fact
that they are
now
that the Roman exile is not something that eliminates the original קדושה
kedusha and therefore we still have the קדושה kedusha of ארץ ישראל,
Eretz Yisrael, which means that תרומה truma is still דאורייתא. de'oraita. That's
the position. ואמר רבי יוחנן מן תנא סדר עולם, Ve'amar Rabbi Yochanan
man tana Seder Olam, which who are we talking about in סדר
עולם? Seder Olam? And as David said, maybe this is the
attribution of סדר עולם Seder Olam being the entire book סדר עולם,
Seder Olam, it could also be
this specific ברייתא. braita. In any case, רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yosi. רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yosi is the one who says סדר עולם. Seder Olam.
Therefore, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi does hold תרומה בזמן הזה truma b'zman
hazeh, is דאורייתא. de'oraita. And therefore, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says I
don't have any problem, oops I tapped the microphone. Therefore,
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says I don't have any problem with the
ברייתא braita you brought. That ברייתא braita is not in accordance with
the position that I'm discussing. So we say וסבר רבי יוחנן דרבנן
לא בעינן ריבויא? Vesavar Rabbi Yochanan derabbanan lo ba'inan ribuya? What about
the position that okay, according to the רבנן, rabbanan,
so fine, in that ברייתא braita with the baskets and the סאה
se'ah that fell into the baskets, right? Alright, so you say that's
not the position of רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosi, which is the position
that I'm discussing. But at the same time, okay, so you admit
that it's דרבנן. derabbanan. So if that's the case, then surely you
should need a רוב rov in order to allow it, because otherwise
you have the possibility that the תרומה truma fell into the חולין
chullin and you have something, you have a mixture דמאי, demai,
and you shouldn't be able to eat it because you don't have
a רוב. rov. So what does רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan not think
that we need
a רוב rov when דרבנן? derabbanan? והתנן מקוה שיש בו ארבעים סאה
Vehatnan mikveh sheyesh bo arba'im se'ah מכוונות, mechuvvanot, נתן סאה ונטל סאה,
Natan se'ah venatal se'ah, כשר. kosher. ואמר רבי יהודה בר שילא אמר
רב אסי אמר רבי יוחנן עד רובו. Ve'amar Rabbi Yehuda ber Shila
amar Rav Assi amar Rabbi Yochanan ad rubbo. So we have a
משנה mishna in מקוואות Mikvaot that says in a מקוה mikveh if
you pour, so you have a מקוה mikveh that's 40 סאה, se'ah,
which is a כשר kosher מקוה. mikveh. And then you take a
סאה se'ah of something that would normally be פוסל את המקוה posel
et hamikveh like fruit juice or something like that and you pour
it into the מקוה. mikveh. And then you scoop out a סאה
se'ah of the new mixture of fruit juice and 40 סאה se'ah
of מקוה mikveh water and you pull it out, you still have
a כשר kosher מקוה, mikveh, even though at this point what you've
really done is you've reduced the amount
of water that's not מים שאובים, mayim she'uvim, that's not drawn water
in the מקוה mikveh because you have something else in
it. And רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says about this, you can do
this until it is the majority of it
is no longer מקוה mikveh water. That's how far you can go.
Why the majority? Because apparently, well because מים שאובים, mayim she'uvim, the
problem of drawn water is a דרבנן derabbanan problem, it's not a
דאורייתא de'oraita problem, and therefore you can go until the רוב. rov.
By the way, there's a תוספות Tosafot here who asks a very
difficult קשיא kashya on this particular issue in terms of yes, maybe
מים שאובים mayim she'uvim is דרבנן, derabbanan, but the case of this
משנה mishna is actually talking about fruit juice or something else, which
is actually דאורייתא. de'oraita. They come up with not such great answers,
but I think the question is a valuable question just to keep
in mind. In any case,
so we say
עד רובו, ad rubbo, מאי לאו Mai lav דנשתייר רובו denishtayer rubbo
that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan demands that
the
What's רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan saying when he says it needs to
have until you've taken until
there's a majority? He says it means you shouldn't take shouldn't have
taken out most of the מקוה mikva water. But if it's half
and half, that's still okay. So you don't need a רוב, rov,
it's okay for it to be half and half. And therefore this
ברייתא braita doesn't bring a קשיא kashya on רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
saying that דרבנן d'rabbanan don't need a רוב. rov. ואיבעית אימא, V'iba'it
eima,
and if you want... wait, didn't you say that the תוספות Tosafos
says that this is a דאורייתא d'ora'ita case? The תוספות Tosafos say
that fruit juice is a דאורייתא d'ora'ita case because they come up...
so it doesn't mean... so really I mean this isn't an answer?
No, it has to be... I mean the תוספות Tosafos קשיא kashya
is an important קשיא kashya from the point of view of the
משנה mishna elsewhere,
but in terms of the way that the גמרא Gemara is treating
this, I mean it's certainly is it is certainly accepted as a
reasonable answer to the question. So we have to assume that רש"י's
Rashi פירוש peirush when he says מים שאובים דרבנן הוא, mayim shu'uvim
d'rabbanan hu, that's the way they're reading this ברייתא, braita, sorry this
משנה. mishna. The way the תוספות Tosafos solves the problem is I
mean they don't have a great answer for it, it's a קשיא,
kashya, it's a big קשיא kashya in terms of what exactly we
can do with this with this משנה mishna and how we solve
the problem of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. But in but in any
case... right, practically in a real מקוה mikva you're not putting in
fruit juice anyway, you're just putting in water. Yeah, in terms of
the practical הלכה halacha it's not it's not going to be an
issue.
Okay,
ואיבעית אימא, V'iba'it eima, I have another answer and this will be
a fine answer. We say שאני הכא, shani hacha, this case is
not an example. Why? The rather the case of the תרומה truma
falling into the חולין chullin is not a problem דאיכא למימר שאני
אומר d'ika l'meimar shani omer because we can rely on the possibility
of the fact that תרומה truma fell from the תרומה truma basket
and חולין chullin fell into the חולין chullin basket. We don't have
to start breaking our heads about whether or not the תרומה truma
might have fallen into the חולין chullin and the חולין chullin might
have fallen into the תרומה, truma that kind of thing. So long
as there's a possibility that they that they fell into the right
baskets, we don't have to worry. Even a 50% possibility? That's what
רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, that's what the suggestion רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
seems to be adopting here and רש"י Rashi embraces that that answer.
In other words, so
long as in when you have a ספק, safek, excuse me, when
it was possible at least in this particular case to say this
is what happened, right, it is it remains a possibility, we can
rely on that as opposed to a case that appears in the
משנה mishna that the תוספות Tosafos brings where there is
one one basket I guess of תרומה truma, and two סאין
se'in that fell into it and how do we handle that situation?
Right? When you have two baskets, one of חולין, chullin, one of
תרומה, truma and two סאין, se'in, you can say חולין לתוך חולין
נפל, תרומה לתוך תרומה נפל. chullin l'toch chullin nafal, truma l'toch truma
nafal. Charlie? This would seem to bring the possibility of many leniencies
in other areas of הלכה halacha if they applied this principle to
those areas. Well, it didn't say it's unlikely, it's equal, right? There's
two baskets and two סאין. se'in. It doesn't mention probabilities at all.
It's a 50% chance as opposed to if there is let's say
10 baskets of חולין chullin and only you know what I mean
only one of תרומה truma, then we wouldn't say the same thing.
Right, I mean I don't know actually and I don't know exactly
how far we're willing to take this principle or if this is
an explanation that the גמרא Gemara is going to use to explain
why רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is confident in this case as opposed
to other cases. Now ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish is not confident in this explanation, although the explanation
appears in the ברייתא. braita. So wait, I'm so just getting this
back to our משנה. mishna. What does that have to do with
the אנדרוגינוס androgynos in this again? So the אנדרוגינוס androgynos we said
can feed his wife תרומה, truma right? רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said
he can even feed his wife מנות כהונה, manot kehuna, right? The
real קודש, kodesh, right? ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says no way, he
can't feed his wife real קודש. kodesh. So then the discussion that
they had, which I wasn't here with you for, seems to indicate
that ריש לקיש Reish Lakish or רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is holding
תרומה בזמן הזה דאורייתא. truma b'zman hazeh d'ora'ita. Right? In order to
discuss תרומה truma, בזמן הזה, bizman hazeh we went into this discussion
of the סאה se'ah of תרומה truma that fell into the קופות
kupot of תרומה truma and חולין chullin or the סאה se'ah of
תרומה truma and חולין chullin that fell into the קופות kupot of
תרומה truma and חולין. chullin.
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said that's not even רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yossi.
I'm discussing the position of רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yossi. רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yossi clearly holds תרומה בזמן הזה דאורייתא truma b'zman hazeh d'ora'ita as
we see in סדר
עולם. Seder Olam. The גמרא Gemara then just asks a parenthetical question.
In which is, okay, let's call that דרבנן. d'rabbanan. Let's call that
the position that disagrees with רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yose. You're still not
requiring a רוב. rov. Why don't you require a רוב, rov, רבי
יוחנן? Rabbi Yochanan? And the answer is
either because there's רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan indeed does not require a
רוב rov for a דרבנן, d'rabbanan, right? Like we saw in the
case of the מקווה. mikvah. Or the possibilities are רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan is relying on this position of שאני אומר, She'ani Omer, that
you can say, oh maybe תרומה truma fell into תרומה truma and
חולין chulin fell into חולין. chulin. Those are the two possibilities. Why
can't you say the same thing over here, שאני אומר She'ani Omer
that an אנדרוגינוס androgynos is male, or whatever it is?
So there is a question about how we hold with an אנדרוגינוס
androgynos in terms of... so we're going to see a little bit
later that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose has another position on an אנדרוגינוס
androgynos and so on. But it doesn't appear that אנדרוגינוס androgynos is
the same kind of ספק safek as we're talking about in the
question of תרומה truma and חולין. chulin. Why not? Why can't you
do the same thing? Meaning if it's just a way of saying
שאני אומר, She'ani Omer, say it here too.
Well, but it's different. So one of them... in the case of
the תרומה, truma, you actually have a ספק safek about an event.
And in the case of אנדרוגינוס, androgynos, you have a ספק safek
about whether the person was a particular thing and there's not an
event that occurred. They got born. Yeah, well, yeah, but that's not
the ספק, safek, right? The ספק safek we know that he was
born, we just don't know what... what an אנדרוגינוס androgynos is. A
ספק safek on status is not the same as a ספק safek
on an event. Right, that's a good answer. I didn't actually think
of that.
Now we go back to the question of the אנדרוגינוס. androgynos. We
say...
sorry, תנן, Tnan, back in our
משנה. mishna. אנדרוגינוס נושא... Androgynos noseh...
So we're now questioning, testing the waters again. What is the story
with this אנדרוגינוס? androgynos? Is the אנדרוגינוס androgynos essentially male? Do we
treat the אנדרוגינוס androgynos essentially male, or do we treat the אנדרוגינוס
androgynos as a ספק? safek? So to say אנדרוגינוס נושא, androgynos noseh,
the hermaphrodite can marry somebody, that suggests that לכתחילה lechatchila they can
go and get married, which means that they are essentially male.
So the גמרא Gemara says תני אם נשא. Tani im nasa. You
should treat that as not as a לכתחילה lechatchila but as a
דיעבד. di'avad. If the אנדרוגינוס androgynos got married, then it counts. והא
נושא קתני? V'ha noseh k'tani? So but it says נושא. noseh. What
are you going to do about that?
So you say ולטעמיך מאי אהא אבל לא נישא? u'letamech ma achava
aval lo nisa? What about the position of... if you want to
say, okay, well it says נושא, noseh, at the end it says
but an אנדרוגינוס androgynos is not wedded, an אנדרוגינוס androgynos weds but
is not wedded. So the language of לא נישא, lo nisa, right,
in passive, is... is the לשון lashon of דיעבד. di'avad. If it
happens afterwards, you don't allow it to be a case.
אלא מאי? Ella mai? What do we say about this? נישא דיעבד
נושא נמי דיעבד. Nisa di'avad, noseh nami di'avad. Both of these cases
are דיעבד. di'avad.
אמרי לא נושא לכתחילה משמע אבל לא נישא דיעבד נמי לא. Amri
lo noseh lechatchila mashma, aval lo nisa di'avad nami lo. So maybe
you could say נושא noseh is לכתחילה, lechatchila,
right? You could say, oh,
the אנדרוגינוס androgynos shouldn't marry לכתחילה, lechatchila, and
but if they were wedded, they shouldn't even... בדיעבד be'di'avad wouldn't matter
at all. In other words, בדיעבד be'di'avad maybe they can be נושא,
noseh, but בדיעבד be'di'avad they can't be wedded.
Like kind of לא זו אף זו? lo zu af zu? Yeah,
something like that. So we have a new question. והא מי תני
סיפא V'ha mi'tani seifa רבי אליעזר אומר אנדרוגינוס חייבין עליו סקילה כזכר.
Rabbi Eliezer omer androgynos chayavin alav sekila k'zachar. Right? רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer says very straightforwardly that an אנדרוגינוס, androgynos, if a man sleeps
with him, or if a woman sleeps with an אנדרוגינוס androgynos who's
married, right, you get סקילה sekila for that like a normal זכר.
zachar. So רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer's position is that an אנדרוגינוס androgynos
is male. Right? If he's stating that, that must suggest that there's
some disagreement or some difference of opinion between רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
and תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. So we say מכלל דתנא קמא מספקי
מספקא ליה. mikhlal d'Tanna Kamma meispaki meispaka lei.
So that would suggest that תנא קמא Tanna Kamma is in question,
מספקי מספקא ליה. meispaki meispaka lei. So we say no, בין למר
בין למר מפשט פשיטא ליה. bein l'mar bein l'mar mipshat pshita lei.
Everybody agrees that an אנדרוגינוס androgynos is
male, מפשט פשיטא ליה. mipshat pshita lei. איכא בינייהו, Ika beinihu, the
disagreement is סקילה משני מקומות. sekila mishnei mekomot. Do you get סקילה
sekila depending on the kind of sexual activity that you
have
with the
אנדרוגינוס? androgynos? So we say מה סבר חייבין עליו סקילה משני מקומות,
ma savar chayavin alav skila mishnei mekomot, probably the תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma who says that, right, no matter how you have sex with
the androgynous you're going to get סקילה skila for that; ומה סבר
כזכר, u'ma savar kezachar, one says specifically you have sex sort of
in the male way. אמר
רב, Amar Rav,
so we have extra time I guess I have to ask you,
how does Rabbi Linzer deal with, I mean Rabbi Linzer got us
through basically an extra עמוד amud last time. Just plow on ahead,
yeah. Okay, let's do it. Not too far ahead. We'll get a
דף daf ahead. I don't think we're going to get a דף
daf ahead, I'm not concerned that that's where we are, I just
want to know like this would be the place to stop if
you guys want to go get coffee early, or we'll continue. Keep
going. All right. אמר רב. Amar Rav. Yeah, I just have a
sort of a form's question but there's more stuff exploring here about
this שני מקומות. shnei mekomot. There
are different, there are actually you like to think of the types
of sex the גמרא Gemara considers as also שלא כדרכה shelo kedarka
like what you might. So yes, correct. So there's four possibilities.
And
you wonder if there isn't some
being on the receiving end if you will, the being the androgynous
in those two ways. I don't know what the
two
places then.
No, it could be, it could be that the two places, it
could be that that's two places, it could be
or the male...
He's not talking about שלא כדרכה. shelo kedarka. No, that's
not,
no,
it could be that. That's how Steinsaltz interprets it. It could be,
it could be the other way, but I guess... Artscroll says even
according to the first obvious one is if he uses the penis.
Right, that's number one, that's not what... No, no, Artscroll says that
as well. That's not what... what רש״י Rashi says is אפילו בנקבותו,
afilu binekeivuto, oh, sorry. אף רש״י Af Rashi says אפילו בנקבותו וטעם
מפורש
לקמן בגמרא. afilu binekeivuto ve'ta'am meforash lekaman bagemara.
If you have anal sex that's a different, is that also סקילה?
skila?
Yes. They noted actually anal or vaginal actually be three ways. So
yes, I mean I agree with you, something is being left out
regardless of whether you interpret that what we're talking about here is
anal or vaginal or
whatever, but whether you're basically saying if you treat the androgynous as
a woman. So there's no...
they're not assuming it's the other way around and they're never looking
at that. That would be the case... treating the androgynous as a
male and his marrying... Right, but that's not written in the גמרא.
Gemara. That is the interpretation that's found elsewhere. Well, where's the רש״י?
Rashi? The רש״י Rashi is the last רש״י Rashi of, or the
second to last רש״י Rashi on the עמוד. amud.
He doesn't give us much to go by. He says אפילו בנקבותו
afilu binekeivuto which would suggest vaginal. You never look at the next
one. במקום זכרות ובמקום נקבות לא. bimkom zachrut uvimkom nekeivah lo. Yes,
exactly. Meaning רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says סבר כזכר. savar kezachar.
What does that mean? במקום זכרות. bimkom zachrut. Right, meaning in the
place of the masculine... Or
it would be vaginal sex with the androgynous and he's not חייב
chayav because that's like... That's the position of רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer.
That's the position of רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. But still that asks
about the position of רבנן. Rabanan. It's not obvious. But then if
it's contrasting that,
then the... then it'd be anyway. The question... any single which way?
Yes, according to רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. The question is what does
the תנא קמא... Tanna Kamma... according to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer you're
okay if you had sex with him through female organs. If רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer disagrees with the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, that means
the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says no matter what way you did
it, you're חייב. chayav. Okay, but the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma discusses
שני מקומות. shnei mekomot. The question is does שני מקומות shnei mekomot
mean any which way or does שני מקומות shnei mekomot meaning like
there's always an איסור issur of homosexuality which is anal. So that
makes... with everybody. So if the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma is agreeing
with רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that means even if you... look but
שלא כדרכה shelo kedarka
is not a problem with women.
Oh, I see. But the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma agrees that... the
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma agrees, yes. All right, he is the... as
the penetrator and the... that's not what the גמרא Gemara is talking
about because that's obvious. Uh-huh, got it. Yeah. Mhm. Okay, perhaps. אמר
רב, Amar Rav, ליתא מתניתין כמי ברייתא. leita matnitin kemei brayta. This
משנה mishna does not hold up
considering the ברייתא brayta that I can bring. דתניא, detanya, רבי יוסי
אומר, Rabbi Yossi omer, אנדרוגינוס בריה בפני עצמה הוא, androgynous beryia bifnei
atzma hu, לא הכריעו בו חכמים. lo hichriu bo chachamim.
So after saying this long discussion where רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi *Rabbi
Yose* is going to say that the אנדרוגינוס Androgynus *androgynous* is actually
a male, we... רב Rav, *Rav* brings us a ברייתא Braisa *baraita*
that says that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose *Rabbi Yose* himself says that
an אנדרוגינוס *androgynous* is actually a third category and I don't know
if we'd call it intersex but some other thing that is not...
that the חכמים chachamim *chachamim* have not decided it as female or
male. So we say אדרבה *adraba*, ליתני לברייתא מקמי מתניתין *leisne l'baraita
mikamei matnitin*. Why should the... why should the ברייתא Braisa *baraita* dominate?
Why shouldn't the משנה Mishna *mishna* dominate? מדשבק רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose
*mide'shavkei Rabbi Yose*... so right? I mean, you have two equal sources.
By the way, people like to talk about the question of like,
is the משנה Mishna *mishna*... does the משנה Mishna *mishna* have some
kind of
authority
over the ברייתות braitos, *baraitot*?
And I don't know, I've heard people mention situations where it does,
but in many, many situations in the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*, and I
would say in most, it's very clear that the משנה Mishna *mishna*
and the ברייתות braitos. *baraitot* are considered to be totally שקולים *shkulim*.
They have... they're completely equal. So why does the משנה Mishna *mishna*
dominate? Ask רבי Rebbe *Rebbi*. I mean, we don't know how things
are chosen to be in the משנה Mishna *mishna* and how things
are chosen not to be in the משנה Mishna *mishna*.
Maybe that was the position of the משנה Mishna, *mishna*, but the
ברייתא Braisa, *baraita* is considered to be a perfectly equal source. That's
why we have a תוספתא Tosefta, *Tosefta*, which says all kinds of
things that we think, you know, were left out inappropriately that really
ought to be still canonized or something like that. Are there things
that you think were left out inappropriately that should have been in
the משנה Mishna, *mishna*? Many of them in the תוספתא Tosefta *Tosefta*.
I don't know if you can say everything in the תוספתא Tosefta
*Tosefta*, but the תוספתא Tosefta. *Tosefta* is a collection of ברייתות braitos
*baraitot* that adds material to the משנה Mishna, *mishna*.
So we say why do you... right, there's no assumption here that
the משנה Mishna. *mishna* is authoritative. We say why should you... why
should you consider the ברייתא Braisa *baraita* to be authoritative? Consider the
משנה Mishna. *mishna* to be authoritative. They're equal. So we say מדשבק
רבי יוסי לבר זוגיה שמע מינה הדר ביה *mideshavkei Rabbi Yose levar
zugya shma mina hadar bei*. From the fact that רבי יוסי *Rabbi
Yose* in... in the משנה Mishna *mishna* was talking together with רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* and now in the ברייתא Braisa. *baraita*
is talking alone, that tells us
that...
that he has... that he's gone back, he's changed his mind. Because
if this was really a... You mean his partner did, right? No,
he did. רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yose* changed his mind and in the
משנה Mishna *mishna* רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yose* and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
*Rabbi Shimon* seem to suggest that the אנדרוגינוס *androgynous* is a male,
and here he's saying that it's not, that it's a בריה בפני
עצמה *birya bifnei atzmah*. So the תוספות *Tosafot* say okay, but say
that רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* originally... say that רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yose*
originally had his own position and then he changed his mind to
join רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*. And they don't have an answer to
that, they say it's a... they say it's a difficult question.
Yeah, I won't get into the רש"י Rashi *Rashi* though. So let's
come back to the משנה Mishna, *mishna* question for a second. Do
we know if... or do we think that רבי *Rebbi* deliberately left
out ברייתות braitos. *baraitot* or does it just not work with the
משנה Mishna *mishna*? I mean, something has to be... I mean, it's
clear that ברייתות Braitot *baraitot* were left out. It's hard to believe
that רבי *Rebbi* didn't know at least some of them. He organized
every single ברייתא Braisa *baraita* that he knew? There are a lot
of ברייתות *baraitot* that just aren't in the משנה Mishnah
*mishna*. The impression that I get is that's kind of why he
did it in the first place. Sorry? That's why he did it
in the first place. What position? Yeah, go ahead, explain. Why did
he... why did he compile a written collection? So there are... there
are various explanations. Well, wait, first of all, the משנה Mishnah? *mishna*
wasn't written. It's really important to understand that the משנה Mishnah *mishna*
was oral. He canonized a certain collection of oral material to be
sort of the official code,
but it certainly wasn't... he didn't change it from oral to written.
It was all... it remained oral for years and years.
But... when did that happen? What's that? This change? When was it
written? It was written down, the first kind of evidence that we
have of it being written down is in the time of the
גאונים *Geonim*, they start saying, oh, there are these written manuscripts. The
גאונים *Geonim* in their ישיבות *yeshivot* are still using תנאים *Tannaim*. They're
still listening to people recite it orally. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
was also not written? The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* was not recited... was
not used in a written form in the ישיבות *yeshivot* of the
גאונים *Geonim*,
although there were... I mean, the גאונים *Geonim* do make reference to
manuscripts that have gotten around. I should say that this is not
100% the scholarly consensus across the board,
but, you know, there is... it is largely... it is largely agreed
among scholars that the משנה Mishnah *mishna* was basically an oral text
until after the time of the גמרא *Gemara*. Meaning it was an
official oral text? Yes, it was a canonized oral text. In other
words, instead of just saying what your teacher taught you, what his
teacher taught him and so on, we're just saying the collection
of... It was a set text that you kind of recited orally.
So was that revolutionary?
Yes, for תורה שבעל פה, Torah she-be-al peh תורה שבעל פה had
always been something that was teacher to student, you kind of learned
the Torah of your master and so on, or you learned the
Torah of the teachers who you circulated among. There was no sense
that there was any kind of order to any of it, there
was no sense that there was any kind of
organization to it or even some sense that any part of it
was a particular canonized group
that
everybody has to know משניות Mishnayos and then you want to go
around picking up ברייתות, okay, that's fine.
Is this what we would for lack of a better word call
a traditional perspective? In other words, this is kind of news to
me because I always thought...
I mean, listen, there's plenty of דף יומי Daf Yomi going on.
I would say that it's not untraditional. I think that people have
made the assumption that collecting the משנה Mishnah. is written down. But
from traditional I mean it's not what I learned as a child.
Yes, okay, so I mean there are people who have made the
mistake and perpetuated the mistake that the משנה Mishnah, is clearly a
written
text, but in the איגרת Iggeres of רב שרירא גאון, Rav Sherira
Gaon,
the letter that רב שרירא גאון Rav Sherira Gaon in the 10th
century wrote to people in Kairouan
in North Africa explaining to them how the משנה Mishnah came to
be written, it seems pretty clear that he refers to the משנה
Mishnah
as oral
and not written down.
And you don't find in the ראשונים Rishonim that there's reference to
רבי having written it. It's not like something that's such a traditional,
we're not
taking a stand against the Orthodox to say the משנה Mishnah was
oral. Charlie? Yeah, I'm listening. The oldest manuscript of the משנה Mishnah
we have is 10th century. Yes. But
that manuscript was copied from a manuscript, that creates an upper
bound on how long it could have been oral, or strictly oral.
There is a fragment of חולין Chullin from the 8th century. So
we don't know who was the first person to
write any of it, משנה Mishna or
what I can say is that Dr. Shlomo Naeh, Hebrew University, and
also Hartman, I'm not sure
where he is most of his time, wrote a very important article
years and years ago where he demonstrated that the organization of the
ספרא, Sifra, the מדרש הלכה Midrash Halacha on ויקרא Vayikra is
original organization is based on the number of words that appear that
after a certain number of words then they say, okay, מגילה ב,
Megilla Beis, okay, מגילה ג, Megilla Gimmel, and the only reason why
you would divide something based on number of words is if it's
written down. In other words, you get to the end of what
a standard length of paper would be and then you move on
to your next piece of paper. So that is pretty convincing in
indicating that very early as early as those organizations go, which is
pretty early, although again, it's not clear that that organization existed at
the time of the משנה, Mishna but as early as that organization
goes, the ספרא Sifra was being written. That's sort of the earliest
proof we have of a text
being on paper. Yes, okay, so the משנה, Mishna at least according
to this גמרא, the ברייתא Braisa, has even standing with the משנה,
Mishna for whatever reason wasn't included in the משנה. Right. And תוספתא,
Tosefta does that have equal standing to the... I mean תוספתא's Tosefta.
just more ברייתות. Okay, so
ברייתא Braita. and תוספתא Tosefta are the same thing? Well, not all
ברייתות are in the תוספתא. Tosefta Everything that is in the תוספתא
is a ברייתא, Braita right? Not every ברייתא Braita. is included in
the תוספתא. The תוספתא is another canonized text, another attempt to create
some kind of canon around the משנה. That's it. The תוספתא is
a collection of ברייתות. Charlie? Yeah, Steinsaltz notes in this particular case
indicates that the ראשונים Rishonim are all over the place on this
issue of do they follow a משנה or ברייתא. Braita Uh-huh. And
I wonder if the same ראשונים Rishonim would generally have the same
position for other cases where the משנה disagreed with a ברייתא brought
later on. Some of them are clearly following משנה, some are... So
it depends, I guess it depends if they're holding some kind of
principled position about משנה versus ברייתא, which I doubt. It seems more
likely that they would try to figure out how this
Okay,
so we
say. Wait, did I answer your actual question? Because I cut, I
got it there in the middle of the, I stopped you in
the middle of the, okay. ושמואל אמר ליתא לברייתא דקמי מתניתין. U'Shmuel
amar leita le'braita dekamei matnitin. שמואל Shmuel says I actually think that
the משנה
has authority over the ברייתא. אדרבה ליתא
למתניתין דקמי ברייתא. Aderaba leita le'matnitin dekamei braita. Why would you consider
either of them to be authoritative? They're equal. דהשמיענא ליה
לכולי דחייש ליחידאה. de'hashmi'anei lei lekulai dekha'ish le'yachida.
Because we have a position that שמואל Shmuel in general has the
position that if we have two positions we should try to be
מחמיר machmir for the
position, a דעת יחיד. dat yachid. This is a little interesting. שמואל's
Shmuel position is, שמואל's Shmuel case is, they're contradicting each other.
Right, exactly, we have, it's not the case of a דעת יחיד
dat yachid where somebody is like we have a general position and
then a slightly more מחמיר machmir position somewhere else, this is a
position where one person says one thing in one place and another
thing in another place and the question is okay, did he change
his mind? Why was he saying two different things? But in terms
of the הלכה, halacha, the גמרא seems to be saying, right, why
should שמואל Shmuel be honoring the משנה? Probably שמואל Shmuel should be
going in terms of the more מחמיר machmir position. So we say,
and this now gets back to our discussion of ברייתות and משניות,
Mishnayot, הני מילי דלא מיתקרה מתניתין. hani milei d'lo mitakra matnitin.
This is a, this counts in a case where we don't cause
the משנה to be overturned. אבל כי מיתקרה מתניתין לא חייש. aval
ki mitakra matnitin lo chash. But if we're going to cause a
משנה to be overturned, לא חייש. la chash. So
although שמואל Shmuel is חושש choshesh for a דעת יחיד dat yachid
in terms of being מחמיר, machmir,
excuse me,
he all, apparently according to this he would only do that in
a case where it is the דעת יחיד dat yachid appears in
the משנה. But if it's a דעת יחיד dat yachid that appears
as a ברייתא and a משנה, then he would hold with the
משנה that contradicts the ברייתא. Yes, meaning the דעת יחיד dat yachid
contradicts in a ברייתא contradicts a משנה that has a more lenient
but more general opinion. שמואל Shmuel would say the fact that it's
both the general opinion and it's also in the משנה gives it
extra weight. אמרי
בי רב משמיה דרב הלכה כרבי יוסי באנדרוגינוס ובהרכבה. Amri bei Rav
mishmei de'Rav halacha k'Rabbi Yossi b'androgynus u'v'harkava. What does אמרי בי רב
משמיה דרב Amri bei Rav mishmei de'Rav mean? So there, so we'll
actually, we're going to talk about who is בי רב Bei Rav
when we talk about the school of רב, Rav? but traditionally when
we have lots of places in the גמרא where they make reference
to
the school of this חכם chacham and the school of that חכם.
chacham. Yeah, I understand, but would you expect בי רב Bei Rav
to be quoting רב? Rav. Not always, I mean, look at רב
הונא, Rav Huna, רב הונא Rav Huna quotes, quotes שמואל. Shmuel. I
mean, בי, we're going to say that בי רב Bei Rav is
רב הונא. Rav Huna. But just because they're בי רב Rav, doesn't
mean that they'll necessarily be quoting רב. They are the, the
בית מדרש beit midrash of רב, but that, they may, they still
have plenty of other חכמים who they make reference to.
And there's a lot of cross-pollination, by the way, between סורא Sura
and נהרדעא Nehardea to the point where, you know, we know who
belongs to which school in many cases, but we don't necessarily expect
them always to quote their רביים. rebbes.
So he says הלכה כרבי יוסי באנדרוגינוס ובהדרכה halacha k'Rabbi Yossi b'androgynus
u'v'hadrakha ובהרכבה, u'v'harkava, sorry, in the case of the hermaphrodite and the
case of
grafting. ושמואל אמר בקושי ובקידוש. U'Shmuel amar b'koshi u'v'kidush. And שמואל Shmuel
says the הלכה halacha is like רבי יוסי in cases of a
woman who is giving birth with difficulty or in a case of
a mixed field. אנדרוגינוס ובקידוש u'v'kidush you mean like כלאים? kilayim? דקדש
אמרה תורה. de'kadesh amra Torah. That's right, it's כלאי הכרם, kilei hakerem,
right, and we'll see the case. So we say אנדרוגינוס הא דאמרן.
androgynus ha de'amran.
The hermaphrodite, that's the one that we've said
already. הרכבה דתנן אין נוטעין ואין מבריכין ואין מרכיבין ערב שביעית פחות
משלושים יום לפני ראש השנה ואם נטע והבריך והרכיב יעקור. harkava d'tnan
ein notein ve'ein mavrichin ve'ein markivin erev shvi'it pachot mishloshim yom lifnei
Rosh Hashanah ve'im nata ve'hivrich ve'hirkiv ya'akor. We have a general, a
position of the משנה that says that you can't plant or clear
virgin territory or graft on the year, on the אלול Elul leading
up to the שמיטה shmita year, so this past אלול Elul we
wouldn't, weren't able to do it, any less, meaning any closer to
ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah than 30 days. When you say clear... מבריכין,
Mavrichin, the use of מבריכין Mavrichin is you have wilderness somewhere
around your property. You want to clear that area for agricultural use,
that's not allowed.
How does ArtScroll say?
Because that would be more like plowing, wouldn't it? No. Like almost?
No.
Why? You're pulling up all kinds of stuff here. Maybe, they say,
well נוטעין, Notin, we can agree on. What do they say? For
מבריכין Mavrichin they say is bend a vine and insert it into
the ground. Bend a vine and insert it into the ground? It
could be, that's not the way Jastrow
explains it. I didn't see the ArtScroll so I don't know, but
that's reasonable.
That's also how Steinsaltz interprets it. Okay, well if that's two against
one, I'm not פשטא דמתנייתא, Pashta Dematnita, so we'll hold with that.
In any case,
if you did these things, certainly makes more sense to say because
then if you did these things then you have to uproot them.
According to you, that's right. What do you uproot? Yeah, sorry, Mark.
רבי יהודה אומר כל הרכבה שאינה קולטת בשלושה ימים שוב אינה קולטת.
Rabbi Yehuda omer kol harkava she'eina koletet bishlosha yamim shuv einah koletet.
So
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says it takes three days to know that
your graft has taken. If it doesn't take in three days, it's
not going to take. רבי יוסי ורבי שמעון אומרים שתי שבועות. Rabbi
Yose veRabbi Shimon omrim shtei shavuot. So they're disagreeing and saying that
maybe you have three days to... you mean you can go all
the way up to... perhaps for grafting. Didn't we have this in
ראש השנה? Rosh Hashanah? In, yeah,
in ראש
השנה Rosh Hashanah י' עמוד ב', yud amud bet, this discussion here.
Yeah, good
memory. רבי יוסי ורבי שמעון אומרים שתי שבועות. Rabbi Yose veRabbi Shimon
omrim shtei shavuot. So
רבי יוסי and רבי שמעון say it's not the whole month,
it's two, rather it's not three days, it's two weeks for a
graft to take. ואמר רב נחמן, Ve'amar Rav Nachman, we have a
position of
רב נחמן. Rav Nachman. אמר רבה בר אבוה לדברי האומר שלושים צריך
שלושים ושלושה. Amar Rabba bar Avuha lidvrei ha'omer shloshim tzarich shloshim vishlosha.
He says actually what we're talking about, everybody agrees that you can't...
the month before שמיטה Shmita you can't do these things. What are
we talking about? What if you did it earlier but it only
takes root afterwards? So if it takes 30 days for a graft
to take root, then you actually need two months before שמיטה Shmita
to allow you to do grafts because you can't have it continuing
to take root even during the 30 days. I understand that. Wait,
why are you making it two months? If it takes 30 days...
so he says everybody agrees that 30 days you're not allowed... what
we call תוספת שביעית, Tosefet Shvi'it, you have an extra month that
you're not allowed to do this kind of planting. So the question
is what if you did the planting, or in this case the
grafting,
on the 31st day? Okay, so the grafting continues to take
place, according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda for three days, according to
רבי יוסי or רבי שמעון for two weeks. So it takes that
long for the graft really to take hold. So in that case
you're really inside the 30-day limit. You're saying everyone agrees with that
part anyway. So right, what רב נחמן Rav Nachman says is we
need to add these numbers that we're getting to an extra 30
days. So if you say it takes 30 days for a graft
to take hold, then what you need is 30 plus 30. לדברי
האומר שלושה צריך שלושה ושלושים לדברי האומר שתי שבועות צריך שתי שבועות
ושלושים. Lidvrei ha'omer shlosha tzarich shlosha ushloshim lidvrei ha'omer shtei shavuot tzarich
shtei shavuot ushloshim. ושמואל אמר בקושי ובקידוש. Ushmuel amar bikoshi uvikidush.
So, basically you're saying sorry... so we basically saying even though the
משנה says 30 days it doesn't mean... essentially, well what רב נחמן
Rav Nachman is saying is that the משנה that says 30 days,
what it's talking about is how long it takes those things
to take root in some way.
And he says this משנה is not talking about our normal תוספת
שביעית, Tosefet Shvi'it, this משנה is talking about the additional things you
need to take into consideration when you're planting things that are going
to take some time. That doesn't sound like that,
but okay. ושמואל אמר קושי ובקידוש. Ushmuel amar koshi uvikidush. קושי דתנן
כמה יהא קישויה, Koshi ditnan kamma yehei kishuyah, right, in the case
of קושי, koshi, what are we talking about? A woman who
starts seeing blood when she's not in her normal menstrual time. So
we normally say that if she sees blood three days in a
row, then is זיבה. Zivah. That's a case of זוב. Zov. This
is all דאורייתא d'Oraitta by the way. In today these הלכות Halachos
are not so relevant. However, we'd say that is a case of
זיבה. Zivah. She needs to sit seven clean days in order to
before she can go to the מקוה Mikvah and so on. However,
if she's pregnant and she turns out that she is in the
process of giving birth, then she then
that blood is not considered to be is not considered to be
זיבה. Zivah. That blood is considered to be part of the birthing
process. So then the question is, okay, but how long before she
starts to see before she gives birth can she be seeing blood
and we say it's still part of her
contractions that's causing the blood? So
and just one other point to point out that this is a
case of continuous blood. So assuming that from the time she starts
seeing blood it's continuous until the time that she actually gives birth,
that is that allows her to that allows us to say oh
it was all about contractions it wasn't ever about זוב. Zov. If
she stops bleeding for a day then we have to say oh
that the previous stuff was actually actually זיבה. Zivah. Okay, so what
we're saying is even so a pregnant woman who's very much pregnant
is in her sixth month she bleeds for like a little bit
that's זיבה? Zivah? Yeah. So we don't say that unless it's. Yeah.
I mean what what we say that like today we say אפילו
טיפת דם כחרדל יושבת עליה שבעה נקיים. afillu tipas dam k'chardal yosheves
aleha shiva nekiyim. Yeah that's what I would imagine for a woman
who's not pregnant. Absolutely, for pregnant women, for everybody else. It's rare
but Paul told me about a case strictly recently of a woman
who kept having periods through her fifth month of pregnancy. Right, I
have heard of that. It's rare but it can happen. So and
we treat those we treat those as according to the normal normal
הלכות Halachos of נדה. Niddah. Now the only thing that you have
a distinction of when a woman is pregnant that's called you have
sort of a and you think that it has more impulse it's
called מסולקת. mesuleket. She is kind of removed from the category of
somebody who bleeds
which would make you maybe think that it's lot far far-reaching, but
it's not. Specifically with regard to וסתות v'saos with regard to the
or like the fact that a woman has to be when she
reaches the time when she normally has her period she has to
be concerned about she doesn't have sex and so on during that
time so that those rules are waived for women who are not
expected to menstruate like pregnant women or nursing women and things like
that. However,
if they do see blood we treat it the same way we
treat all נדה. Niddah.
So the question is how long can this happen? I mean if
she sees blood throughout right shall we said a woman who saw
blood like for a long time right could we if it was
possible could she if she saw blood all the way through her
entire pregnancy would we say oh it was contractions the entire way?
It doesn't make any sense. רבי מאיר אומר או ארבעים או חמישים
יום. Rabbi Meir omer o arbaim o chamishim yom. Rabbi Meir says
either
40 or 50 days. That far back you can already if she
bleeds continuously until the time she gives birth we won't call that
יולדת בזוב yoledes b'zov that she gave birth
in זיבה. Zivah. By the way just במאי נפקא מינה b'mai nafka
mina about יולדת בזוב yoledes b'zov somebody who gives birth when she's
a זיבה ziva is טמא tamei right? What's that? Would that be
the דמי טוהר? demei tohar? So that has נפקא מינה nafka mina
with regards to the דם טוהר dam tohar because if she's בזובה
b'zova then we don't we don't give her any kind of טהרה
tahara until she's actually sees שבעה נקיים. shiva nekiyim. The other thing
is that the actual blood itself has particular מטמא metamei aspects. Blood
of blood of זיבה ziva is מטמא metamei in a way that
blood of נדה niddah is
not. רבי יהודה אומר דיה חודשה. Rabbi Yehuda omer daya chodsha. Rabbi
Yehuda has an interesting position. He says ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh from
the month where she where she
gives birth that's right if from that ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh on.
Oh so does it mean from ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh or does
it mean a month before? So the way רש"י Rashi explains it
is from ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. It could be that he means
just simply a month. He says חודשה. chodsha. So it could be
from whatever the month she's that's a that's a perfectly reasonable explanation.
רש"י gives the other. ורבי יוסי ורבי שמעון אומרים אין קישוי יותר
משתי שבתות. V'Rabbi Yossi v'Rabbi Shimon omrim ein kishuy yoter mishtei shabbatos.
So Rabbi Yossi, Rabbi Shimon say we're talking about אין קישוי יותר
משתי שבתות ein kishuy yoter mishtei shabbatos two weeks. We should stop
here it's 8:30. Yeah. יישר כח. Yasher koach. Okay so
see
you tomorrow.